So let's see how we can use Python
现在，让我们来看看如何使用Python来
to solve our Bacon example. Let's go back to our spreadsheet
解决贝肯数的例子。 让我们回到 刚才的电子表格
and let's have a look at the parts that we like, like this simple VLOOKUP. It's
我们先来来看看 大家都喜欢的部分，例如这简单的VLOOKUP。 这看起来
pretty okay.
还不错。
However, this is problematic, it has two lines and also it depends
可是，这却是挺棘手的，这是因为它不仅有两行，而且它的值也取决于
on those ugly SUMIFs in the other worksheet.
其他工作表里繁琐的SUMIFS 函数。
So, we want to get rid of that and replace that with Python.
所以，我们要把这些都去掉，并用Python来代替它们 。
So let's take this column, select it
我们用鼠标选择这一列，然后
and let's copy it back as values. It's like a test, so we can see if our
把它复制成数值。 这就像一个测试，能让我们看看
Python will do the exact same thing
Python是否能给出
as the original formulas. And we get rid of that and make some room
和原本公式一样的结果。 我们把这些删掉，把空间留给
for our Python code: 'Steps in Python'.
Phython的代码：“Steps in Python”，即“Python的步骤”。
So the question is now, what
现在问题来了，
are we going to do here? What actually are we calculating?
我们这样做的目的是什么？ 我们究竟在计算什么？
And if we think about it, what we're going to calculate here
如果我们仔细想想，我们在这里要计算的是：
is: for each of the movies is there an actor
在每一部电影中, 是否有一个演员
in it, that has a Bacon number that is unequal to
的贝肯数不等于破折号，
a dash, that has a defined Bacon number.
即他的贝肯数是一个有意义的数值。
And in order for us to figure out what to place there in Python,
为了让我们弄清楚究竟要把什么输入Python中
we're going to need the theory glasses.
我们将需要用理论来分析。
So let's go to the blackboard and have a look at what exactly we are calculating. So what
现在，让我们去黑板上看看 究竟我们正在计算什么。 所以呢
we would like to have
我们希望能够
is a function like SUM, that calculates based on the name of the movie,
有一个像SUM的函数， 能根据该电影的片名计算出
the list of actors that are in it, their
电影中每位演员的
Bacon numbers. So what
贝肯数。 那么
is the type of that function?
这个函数属于什么类型的呢？
So let's say all of the steps for a given movie,
先来谈谈对于一部电影，我们的操作步骤应该是怎么样的，
we put in a movie, and what we want to get out
我们输入一部电影的片名，我们想得到的是
is a list of Bacon numbers for that movie.
一份包含该电影演员的贝肯数的列表。
So for instance, for 'Crazy Stupid Love' this list would be
举例来说，对于《疯狂盲目的爱情》这部电影，
one-dash-dash [1--], these are the first three
它的列表将是“1- -”，这些是
rows currently in the spreadsheet. So what we
当前电子表格中的前三行。 所以我们
get is a list
想要的结果是一份
of things. So what is in this list?
列表。 那么这份列表里有什么呢？
It's either a dash, either it's undefined
要不它是一个破折号，表示该演员的贝肯数未知，
or it will be a value.
要不就是一个确定的数值。
And if you remember from the previous types,
如果你还记得我们之前讲的关于“类型”的知识，
lists are quite hard to work with in
用电子表格来运算列表
spreadsheets. You have to use array formulas for that.
是相当困难的工作 。 因为你必须使用数组公式来计算。
But in Python lists are very easy, they're one of the built-in types
但在Python里，列表里是很容易计算的， 因为列表属于Python内置的类型中的一种
and a very easy to manipulate. So something like this: will be easily done
并且非常容易掌握。 所以在Python里
in Python.
这样的事情能很轻松的完成。
If we have that list, one-dash-dash [1--], what we need to
如果我们有那张列表 “1- -”，
calculate
我们需要计算的
is the Bacon number of that list. So let's call that function NextStep,
是该列表的贝肯数。 我们现在把这个函数命名为“NextStep”，
what we put in here
我们在这里输入的
is this list. So we put in the list
就是这张列表。 我们把演员贝肯数的列表输进去
of the Bacon numbers of the actors and what we will get out
我们得到的
is a value. So these are the things that we're going to program
将会是一个值。 所以，这些都是
in Python. Give me a movie and I will give you a list of the Bacon numbers of
我们要在Python 中编程的东西。 给我一部电影的名字，
the actors in it,
我能给出一份该电影所有演员的贝肯数列表；
and give me that list and I will give you the Bacon number of
给我一张列表，我能给出
everyone that is in this movie. So we don't need the theory glasses anymore,
那部电影里每个演员的贝肯数。 所以，我们说完了理论，
let's go back to Excel and have a look at how function defining works in Python.
让我们再回到Excel看看 在Python里应该如何使用定义函数。
So let's power up a shell, we click Python Shell
让我们启动shell，
in DataNitro and now we can define functions.
点击在DataNitro的Python Shell，现在我们可以来自定义函数了。
So let's start with an easy one, we say we wanna have a function 'plusone',
让我们先从简单的开始，比方说我想新建一个函数“plusone”，
where we put in something and the result is that something
当我们把一个数值输入该函数，而结果就是
plus one. So this is very much like defining our own SUM function or our own
所输入的数值加上1。 所以这是跟自定义求和函数（SUM）或
MIN function. We can put something in, and we get a result.
自定义最小值函数（MIN）是十分相似的。 我们输入某个数值， 就会得出相应的结果。
For example, now if we ask Python what is this,
例如，如果我们现在问Python 这是什么，
it knows that plusone is a function and if we put something in, for instance we get
它知道“plusone”是一个函数，而 如果我们把任何数值输入此函数里，
the plusone of 5
比如5，我们将得到的是5 加上1的结果
the result is 6. So, it's a bit cryptic maybe,
即是6。 也许这听起来有点玄妙
but the idea is that if you define your own functions
但它的道理就是，当你自定义一个函数时
and you can say what do I take in? The number X.
你要这样问自己：我输入的是什么？ 输入的是X这个数值；
And what do I return? That number X plus one.
而我得到结果是什么？ 结果是X加1所得的数值。
And this is the exact same thing, the
同样地，
function defining, that we're going to use to address our Bacon issue.
我们要利用这自定义函数来解决我们的贝肯数问题。
So let's make another shell and let's make another function.
那么我们来新建一个shell，让我们再编一个函数。
And you know what function, the functions that we defined on the blackboard.
你知道那是什么函数， 就是我们在黑板上定义的函数。
We start with AllSteps. AllSteps is a function that takes in
我们先从AllSteps开始。 AllSteps是一个 函数，我们输入
the name of a movie and it returns
电影的名称，它将计算出
all the Bacon numbers of people in that movie.
电影里所有演员的培根数。
So for example, for 'Crazy Stupid Love' the result of this function would be one
例如，当我们输入“疯狂盲目的爱情 ”（ 'Crazy Stupid Love'）时，该函数的运算结果将是
and a dash and another dash [1--]. So we're going to
1-破折号-破折号，即是[1- - ]。 现在我们要
traverse
详细比对
all the lines in our spreadsheet and see if we have a match for our movie.
电子表格中的每一行，看 是否有与我们电影相匹配的一项。
Initially, if we start with the first line of course we haven't found
首先，我们从第一行开始, 很明显没有发现任何匹配，
any matches yet and then with the 'for'
但是当使用“for'语句功能时，
syntax function, this is a Python thing,
这是Python的特点，
we can use everything; we can address every line.
我们可以利用所有东西， 我们可以标注每一行。
So we start at the second line and we go until the twelfth line
我们现在从在第二行开始直到第十二行
and at every line we're going to look is
在每行中，我们要看的是
the value in the second column, so in
在第二列中的值，
the row that we are in, which is 'i', our variable
所以，我们所在的那一行，即是第“i”行的第2列（i是循环变量）
for the loop, in the second column, is the value of that thing that we are
就是我们要找的
inspecting
那部
equal to the movie we have put into our function. So,
刚刚被输入函数的电影名了。 所以，
this should remind you of the SUMIF function,
这应该让你联想到SUMIF函数，
where we're summing a bunch of lines only if it matches
SUMIF函数只对某些符合
a certain value. Well, here we are grabbing a piece of values together
一定条件的数据进行合计。 像这样，如果数据的数值与我们的条件相匹配时
only if it matches a certain value. So what are we adding to our list?
我们就把它们合并求和。 那么，我们应该具体把什么数据添加进这份列表中呢？
Not the name of the movie, but the column right next to it. So the
不是电影的名称，而是它旁边的那一列， 也就是
cell on the row we are inspecting in the third column.
我们正在检查的那一行的第三列的那个单元格
If we have a match, we add this to our list with the append function.
如果找到了相匹配的数值，我们通过追加函数将它添加到列表中。
And if we're done, if all of the rows have been inspected, then
如果所有的行都被检查完毕了，
we return the list of steps. So remind yourself of,
我们将得到一份列表。 大家应该提醒自己，
like the plusone, we put in five we get back six, this is,
像plusone这个函数，我们把5输入进去，得到的结果是6；
we put in a movie we get back a list. So we can put the result of this into a
而在这里，我们把一部电影名输进去，得到的结果是一份列表。 那么 我们可以把所得到的结果作为
variable.
一个变量。
Let's try that. For the movie 'Crazy Stupid Love'
让我们来试试。 我们首先为电影 “疯狂盲目的爱情”创建一个变量，
we make a variable called Steps of Crazy Stupid Love [StepsCSL]
并把它称为“疯狂盲目的爱情的步骤”， 简称为“StepsCSL”
and what we're going to put in that variable
我们输入该变量的，
is the result of our function. The AllSteps
正是我们用函数计算得出的结果。 在AllSteps函数中
applied on 'Crazy Stupid Love'. But here we should
我们能使用‘疯狂盲目的爱情’ 但在这里，我们应该添加引号“ ”
add quotes ["], because it's a string, a text value.
因为它是一个字符串，是一个文本值。
So we hit enter and now the value is
我们按下回车键，现在的值就被保存到变量中了，
saved in our variable and if we ask Python now what is in
如果有人问Python
this variable? The result will be one dash dash [1--],
现在这个变量里有什么？ 其结果将是1-破折号-破折号，即是“1--”
and this is exactly what we wanted, right? The result
而这正是我们想要的结果，对不对？ 输入“疯狂盲目的爱情”的结果
of 'Crazy Stupid Love' is the list one dash dash [1--].
正是列表中的“1--”。
So the first part of our problem is solved,
这样我们 问题的第一部分便得以解决了，
but it is still solved in the Python world,
但我们是用Python来解决这个问题的，
and we would like to have this value back
而我们想要
in the spreadsheet world. So we can do that, we've seen that before, we can edit
结果在电子表格里出现。 我们可以做的是，其实大家之前已经看过了，
the spreadsheet from
就是可以在
Python, we can say: the cell in the
Python里编辑该电子表格，我们可以说，
second column in the fourth row. Oops I'm sorry,
在第二列中第四行的单元格。 哎呀，不好意思说错了，
second row in the fourth column should be the value that we have in our
应该是，在第四列中的第二行
variable.
就是我们变量的值。
And if we hit enter now, immediately the value has been updated.
如果我们现在按下回车键，那个 值将会立即被更新。
And what you see here is that Python can put an entire list in a cell.
大家可以看到， Python能够把整个列表放入一个单元格里。
If you want to do that with Excel we have to use array formulas
如果你想在Excel做到这一点，我们不得不使用数组公式，
as we've seen in videos of previous weeks. Excel cannot put an array, a list
正如我们在之前的视频中所看到的一样。 Excel不能把一个数组，或一个列表
in one cell, you have to give it space to fill up all the cells.
放入一个单元格里，你必须给它空间填满所有的单元格。
This is not the case with Python, we can just take the whole list
这和Python不一样，我们可以直接把整个列表
and put it in a cell. Which is a lot more convenient,
放进一个单元格里。 这样显然方便得多了，
if you are using a lot of list operations like we are.
尤其是当你也像我一样使用大量的列表时。
So let's continue with the second half of our problem. I have cleared
好了，接下来我们继续解决问题的第二部分。 我已经清除了
the shell now, however, we can still
shell里的内容，但是，我们仍然可以
see all the functions that are there. Python has remembered them,
看到在那里的所有函数。 因为Python已经把它们给记住了，
so we still have the AllSteps function and we're going to make a new one now.
所以那里仍然有AllSteps函数， 而我们现在要建立一个新的函数，
We're going to make the function NextStep. As we saw on the blackboard, this is
建立一个叫做NextStep函数。 正如我们在黑板上看到的，我们需要把
a function that takes in the list
刚刚创建的列表输入这个函数
that we have just created and returns
它会
the next value. So we're going to traverse the steps,
得出下一个值。 现在让我们来详细研究所需要的步骤。
one dash dash [1--] in this case, just as we have
我们这里有“1- -”，
traversed the rows in the previous example.
跟之前例子中的一样。
So we use 'for' again, a Python construct that is used for looping,
我们再次使用“for”语句，“for”是一种适用于循环指令的Python结构
and we are inspecting all of the elements in our steps list.
我们正在检查 步骤列表上的每一项。
So if we see something that is not a dash, like a one,
那么如果我们看到一个不等于破折号的值，譬如1，
we know what the result is, right? Then the result should be that value
我们就知道结果了对不对？ 得出的结果应该就是该值加上1。
plus one. So if we see something
即是说， 如果我们看到的值不等于破折号，
unequal to, that is the exclamation mark syntax,
这里用的是感叹号“!”语句，
then we know that we have to return plus one.
那么我们知道返还的值将是该数值加1。
But, what if we see a dash?
但是，如果我们看到的是破折号呢？
We don't know what to return, because the next row
我们不知道应该返还哪一个值，因为下一行
could be a dash or it could be a one. So if we see a dash we don't know
既可以是破折号，也可以是1。 因此，如果我们看到的是破折号
yet,
那么我们暂时还不知到该返还什么，
however, if we've only seen dashes and we haven't returned
可是，如果我们只看到破折号，
anything yet, then we are going to return
而没有返还过任何数值，
a dash, because that exactly expresses what
那么我们将返还一个破折号，
we want.
因为这正是我们想要的。
If everything is a dash the result will be a dash.
即是说，如果所有都是破折号，结果将会是一个破折号。
So we have a function, it is defined, and we still have our variable, one dash
现在我们的函数已被定义好了。我们 还有变量“1 - -”，
dash [1--], that we've made in a previous slide. So
就是在之前的幻灯片得出的那个。 那么
now we can use that, we can call this
现在我们可以使用它了，
function
我们可以把变量输入函数中，
on the variable and it goes like this:
就像这样，
like plusone, we just put the variable in
像plusone函数一样，我们只要把 变量输入进去，
and we get the result. So if we put this list in, our result is 2, which is
就可以得到结果了。 如果我们把这个 列表输入其中，得到的结果将是2，
exactly what we wanted.
正是我们想要的结果。
If we have a movie with three actors, one is Kevin Bacon
如果我们的电影里有三位演员，其中一位是凯文·贝肯
and the other two have an undefined Bacon number, then this movie will give
而其他两位演员的贝肯数未知，
the Bacon number of
那么，这部电影中所有演员的贝肯数
2 to everyone that has played in it.
将会等于2。
So, so far we've been using only the Python shell
到目前为止，我们只用了Python shell这个办法
option but what we can also do is use the editor.
我们其实也可以使用编辑器来解决问题。
Then we don't have to type in the functions on the crazy little line thingy,
这样我们就不必小之又小的行里输入函数了。
we can just type them in a text file and save this, just as you save a spreadsheet.
我们只需要把函数输入文本文件，然后把它们保存下来，就像保存电子表格一样。
You can also save these python files and that's of course a lot easier
你也可以保存这些Python 文件，
than typing them in, because once you've closed the shell
这样做当然比输入它们简单多了，因为一旦你把Shell关闭，
all the functions that you have defined are gone. So we put everything,
你所定义的函数都会消失。 所以我们把这一切，
the same function definitions, now in a file.
包括函数的定义等等，都放入一个文件当中。
And from that file we can run it and put it back into the spreadsheet.
我们可以直接在该文件上运行程序， 并把它输入电子表格里 。
So again, we're going to use a for loop
我们将再次使用 “for”循环语句，
and for all of the lines we're going to
而且为了简化我们即将打印的结果，
print, to make it easy, we're just going to print the number of the row.
我们只打印每行的序号。
Just so you can see how it goes. So we say the value of 'i'
这样做只是为了让你们看看这究竟是怎么运作的。 我们来设定"i”的值，
and 4 is going to be just 'i'.
比如说4是“i”的值
So if we made that, we've saved the file and we hit run,
我们完成了这一步，把文件保存，然后我们点击“运行”，
*whoop* you see at one go all
你们看，所有的“i”都出现在那里了。
the 'i's are there, but I've made a mistake,
但其实，我犯了一个小错误，
I was using "to 12" all the time and I forgot that
我一直用的是“到12”（“to 12”），
it's "until 12" and not "until and including 12". So, this should actually be
我忘了应该用的是“直到12”("until 12")，而不是“直到和包括12”。 因此，这实际上应该是13
13 and so has the function.
函数也是一样的。
So, now we've gone until 13 and you see all of the
好，现在我们运行到13，
rows are filled.
你可以看到所有的行都填满了。
But, of course, we don't want that 'i' in there, what we'd like to have
但是，我们当然不想“i”出现在这里，
is the result of those two functions that we've just defined.
而我们想要的是刚刚定义的那两个函数的结果。
So let's start with the AllSteps again, so we take the
那么我们再次从AllSteps开始，
the value from the second column.
从第二列中取得数值。
So now we have the movies, that's the first step we need,
现在我们有了电影名称，这是我们所需的第一步，
because the name of the movie is what we're going to put into
因为我们将在AllSteps函数里
the AllSteps functions. So here we go, AllSteps.
输入电影的名称。 现在我们把它输入AllSteps。
In it, we're not using a string anymore, but we get the value from the spreadsheet.
在这里，我们不再用字符串了，而是直接从电子表格中获得数值
It's nice right? So now for every movie
看起来很不错吧？ 好了，现在对于每部电影
we have a list of all the actors that are in it and we just need to put that list
我们都有一份它所有演员的列表，
into the NextStep
我们只需要把该列表输入NextStep函数。
function. There we go, we put in the list,
就像这样， 我们把列表输进去了，
now we hit run. Look at that!
现在我们点击运行。 看看这个
The result is exactly the same as the result that we have obtained
得出的结果是和我们之前用
with all the VLOOKUPs and the SUMIFs, but instead of using
VLOOKUP和SUMIFS得到的结果是完全一样的，
a lot of formulas, we just used a little bit of code
之前我们使用了很多公式，
to calculate the values. Why is this code
而这里我们只做了一点点编程就把它算出来了。 为什么这里的编程
easier than VLOOKUP? Because we use constructs like
比VLOOKUP更简便呢？ 因为我们使用的列表和循环结构
a list and a loop that are not native, not natural to spreadsheets.
并不是电子表格本身就有的功能。
These are contracts that are very common in programming, however, if you want to do
这种对比在编程中十分常见。
something like
然而，如果你想要
inspect all the lines of my spreadsheet and do something in a certain case,
检查所有这份电子表格的每一行以及作某些特殊操作的话，
this is not something that spreadsheets are made for. They're made for calculation
这就不是电子表格能胜任的了。 电子表格是用来计算的，
and not really for inspecting values and then changing them
而不是用于检查数值
continuously. So these are scenarios where programming languages are just
以及改变数值的。 在以上提到的这种情况，
a little bit easier.
如果我们使用编程语言的话就会容易一点了。
So what we can do now, we can get rid of those,
所以，我们现在能做的就是
we don't need those ugly SUMIFs anymore. We can select them
去掉那些我们不再需要的SUMIFS 语句，它们实在太难看了。 我们用鼠标来选取它们
and we're done with it, go away, we don't wanna see you anymore. And here,
然后把它们都清除掉，我们不希望再看到你了。 而在这里，
notice how I've put back the VLOOKUPs secretly while you weren't looking,
留言我是如何趁你不留神的时候悄悄地把VLOOKUPS放回原处。
just to show you it one more time, before we get rid of it too. So we don't need
只为了再次演示给大家看我是如何删除它的。 所以我们并不需要
those values anymore. But we don't need to get rid of all of the
这些值了。 但是我们不必清除所有的公式
formulas - some of them are still fine,
有些公式还是有用的，
The  VLOOKUP for instance, the first one that we used,
例如，这条VLOOKUP语句，就是我们使用的第一条公式，
it's fine, it's a simple function, you can use it.
它没有任何问题，只是一个简单的函数，你可以使用它。
But some parts, the ugly parts, we have removed now
但有些冗长的部分，我们已把它们删除了，
and replaced them by this short Python code.
取而代之的是这短短的Python代码。
And you see me in this video I only did the second step,
你们在这个视频里只看到我完成了第二个步骤，
so your challenge for the rest of the week is to extend this Python program
所以我在本周给你的挑战是完成整个Python程序
so that it doesn't just work for two steps, but it works for an
让它不仅运行两 步，而是运行无数步，
unlimited number of steps, or let's say at least until 12, because that's the
或者说至少要到12步，
highest Bacon number there is.
因为那是最大的贝肯数。
So good luck with that homework and see you next week!
祝你做作业好运， 我们下周见！